Kimberly Chapman

Instructional Designer

email: kimberlychapmanb@gmail.com

phone: (847) 951-9225

website: https://kimberly-chapman.com

Technically sophisticated professional with significant training in front-end development and over ten years of teaching, leadership, and consulting experience. Solid portfolio of educational applications designed and developed for a diverse audience of learners that focus on improving users' learning experience and outcomes. Proven ability to use strong and strategic design processes to facilitate completion of projects through all stages, including everything from problem definition and usability principles to ideation and feedback sessions. Keen aptitude for defining learning outcomes, designing educational games, and actualizing concepts from production to product launch. Poised to build communicative and enthusiastic relationships with product stakeholders to ensure efficient attainment of overarching priorities and objectives.

Areas of Expertise

- Instructional Design
- Learning Experience Design
- Multimedia Asset Creation
- UI/UX Design

- Web Accessibility
- Product Mock-ups
- User Journeys
- Agile Methodologies
- Critical Problem Solving
- Inter-department Collaboration
- Project Management
- Stakeholder Communication

Technological Skills

- Web Design and Front-end Programming: HTML/CSS, JavaScript, Python, Python GUI
- Design Software: Adobe Creative Cloud (Illustrator, Photoshop, Premiere), iMovie, Camtasia
- Instructional Design Software/Platforms: Canvas, Articulate (Storyline and 360)
- Project Management Software: Jira, Smartsheet, Projector, Slack

Professional Experience

EVERSPRING PARTNERS

Instructional Designer

September 2021 – Present

- Create innovative online graduate courses for our university partners— collaborating with faculty to align content with learning objectives, build assessments, and create opportunities for interaction and authentic learning.
- Develop multimedia and interactive components, in collaboration with creative services, to increase engagement and comprehension.
- Design online instructional trainings for internal and external use.
- Apply knowledge of front-end programming, design software, and e-learning software and platforms to develop instructional materials.

FREELANCE PRODUCT DESIGN SERVICES

Interactive Learning Designer

September 2020 - August 2021

- Provided a diverse spectrum of product design and development services for clients in need of a learning design expert with a strong background in education, accessible design, and UI/UX design.
- Established and fostered open lines of communication with product stakeholders to gain a comprehensive understanding of requirements and goals.

CHICAGO PUBLIC SCHOOLS

Accessible Technology Designer

August 2018 - June 2019

- Applied advanced knowledge of learning technologies to design multimedia instruction, support student learning processes, measure student success, and inform next instructional moves.
- UI/UX Designer: Pioneered development and implementation of assistive technology tools: including a program that provided students with autologins for applications, and a program that allowed students to create their own tutorials on how to use educational software products.
- Product Developer: Masterminded and championed a method for data analysis that used a
 word frequency counter to enable teachers to quickly identify student growth across multiple
 assessments and data sources.
- Learning Experience Designer: Orchestrated end-to-end design of an exemplar experiential learning and technology unit that was later adopted district wide.

CHICAGO PUBLIC SCHOOLS

Special Education Teacher & District Mentor

August 2011 - June 2019

- Designed engaging curricula that leveraged student strengths to achieve individualized learning goals and master common core standards.
- Mentored new teachers: supporting the onboarding process for new hires.
- Provided professional development on inclusive practices and multimodal learning.
- Established programs to support parents and improve coordination between in-school and at-home learning.

CHICAGO YOUTH PROGRAMS

Educational Consultant

June 2016 - June 2017

- Consulted on the design and implementation of Chicago Youth Program's early literacy program, for children ages 3-6.
- Trained parents and community volunteers on how to implement the program.

Education

Northwestern University

Master of Arts – MA, Learning Sciences, 2020 Honors: magna cum laude (GPA: 4.0)

University of Wisconsin-Madison

Bachelor of Science– BS, Education (Special Education), 2010

Honors: Dean's List